本节我们研究是否可以从更简单的原型
In this segment we ask whether we can
build block ciphers from simpler
比如伪随机数发生器，来构建分组密码
答案是肯定的。一开始
primitives like pseudo random generators.
The answer is yes. So to begin with, let's
我们研究是否可以从伪随机数发生器
构建伪随机函数
ask whether we can build pseudo random
functions as opposed to pseudo random
而不是伪随机置换。我们能否由PRG构建PRF？
permutations from a pseudo random
generator. Can we build a PRF from a PRG?
尽管我们的最终目标是构建一个分组密码
本质上是个PRP
Our ultimate goal though is to build a
block cipher which is a PRP. And we'll get
我们最后会实现之。好，现在我们构建一个PRF
我们从PRG开始
to that at the end. Okay, for now we build
a PRF. So let's start with a PRG that
这个PRG输出长度是输入长度的两倍，其种子就是密钥空间K里的元素
doubles its inputs so the seeds for the
PRG is an element in K and the output is
输出实际上是K里的两个元素
这里我们有发生器的机制
actually two elements in K. So here we
have a schematic of the generator, that
取输入为C和K，然后输出两个K中元素
basically takes his input of C and K, and
outputs two elements, in K as its output.
这个安全的意义是什么？
And now what does it mean for this purity
to be secure, recall this means that
记得其意义是输出与一个K^2中的随机元素
essentially the output is
indistinguishable from a random element
不可区分。其实根据PRG，是非常容易定义
inside of K squared. Now it turns out that
it's very easy to define basically what's
PRF中的一位的。PRF中的一位
called a one bit PRF from this PRG. So
what's a one bit PRF is basically a PRF
就是说PRF的定义域只有一位。好
这个PRF只取一位作为输入
who's domain is only one bit. Okay, so
it's a PRF that just takes one bit as
好，我们说，如果输入位X是0
input. Okay, and the way we'll do it is
we'll say is if the input bit X is zero
我会用左边的输出；如果输入位X是1
I'll put the left output and if the input
bit X is one then I'll put the right
我会用右边的PRF输出。好，我们写成符号的形式
output of the PRF. Okay, in symbols we
basically have what we wrote here. Now it
现在很直接地就看成，事实上如果G是个安全PRG
is straightforward to show, that in fact G
is a secure PRG, then this one bit PRF is
那么这个一位PRF也是安全的。大家想一想
in fact a secure PRF. If you think about
it for a second, this really is
这其实是废话，把同样的事情说了两遍
tautology. Its really just stating the
same thing twice. So I will leave it for
我留给大家思考，说服自己
you to think about this briefly and see
and convince yourself that in fact this
这个定理是正确的。真正的问题是
我们能否构建一个PRF
theorem is true. The real question is
whether we can build a PRF, that actually
它的定义域比一位多。理想情况下，
我们让定义域为128位
has a domain that is bigger than one bit.
Ideally we would like the domain to be 128
就像AES一样。那么问题是我们能否
bits, just say as AES has. So
the question is can we build 128 bit PRF
由一个伪随机数发生器，构建一个128位PRF？
我们来看能不能取得进展
from a pseudo random generator. Well so
let's see if we can make progress. So the
那么我们要做的第一件事是，从一个PRG出发
first thing we're gonna do is we're gonna
say, well again, let's start with a PRG
这个PRG将输入长度翻倍，我们看能否构造一个PRG接受四倍输入
that doubles its input, let's see if we can
build a PRG that quadruples its inputs.
好吧？它从K映射到K^4，而不是K到K^2，好
Okay? So it goes from K to K to the fourth
instead of K to K squared. Okay, so let's
那么我们来看怎么做的。我们从一个初始的PRG开始
see how to do this. So here we start with
our original PRG that just doubles its
扩充它的输入，记住这是个PRG
inputs, now remember that the fact that
this is a PRG means that the output of the
意味着它的输出和K中的两个随机值不可区分
PRG is indistinguishable from two random
values in K. Well, if the output looks
如果输出和K中的两个随机值看上去很像
我们可以对这两个输出再次使用发生器
like two random values in K, we can simply
apply the generator again to those two
那么我们说，对左边的输出应用一次发生器
outputs. So let's say we apply the
generator once to the left output, and
对右边也应用一次。我们称这四元组的输出
once to the rights outputs. And we are
going to call the output of that, this
为G1K。我写下这个发生器生成的符号
quadruple of elements, we are, are going
to call that G1K. And I wrote down in
但大家可以从这幅图里看到
symbols what this generator does, but you
can see basically from this figure,
发生器到底做了什么。现在我们有一个
从K到K^4的发生器
exactly how the generator works. So now
that we have a generator from K to K to
我们有了一个两位的PRF
the fourth, We actually get a two bit PRF.
Namely, what we will do is, we will say,
给定两位，00,01,10或11，会确定
given two bits, 00, 01, 10 or 11, will
imply output the appropriate block that
G1K输出的合适的分组。好，现在我们有了
一个有4种可能输入的PRF
the output of G1K. Okay, so now we can
basically have a PRF that takes four
而不是像前面那样，只有两种可能输入了
possible inputs as opposed to just two
possible inputs as before. So the question
那么问题是为什么这个G1是安全的？
为什么这是个安全的PRG？
you should be asking me is why is this G1
case secure? Why is it a secure PRG? That
那就是为什么这个四元组输出与
随机序列不可被区分
is why is this quadruple of outputs
indistinguishable from random. And so
我们来快速证明一下，以图的形式
let's do a quick proof of this, we'll just
do a simple proof by pictures. So here's
这是我们的发生器，我们试图证明其安全性
our generator that we want to prove is
secure. And what that means is that we
这意味着我们想证明这个分布是与
want to argue that this distribution is
indistinguishable from a random four-tuple
K^4中的随机四元组不可区分。好
我们的目标是证明
in K to the fourth. Okay so our goal is to
prove that these two are
这两个是不可区分的。好，一步一步来
indistinguishable. Well let's do it one
step at a time. We know that the generator
我们知道这个发生器是安全的，因此第一层的输出
is a secure generator, therefore in fact
the output of the first level is
与随机不可区分。换句话说，如果我们用
indistinguishable from random. In other
words, if we replace the first level by
真随机字符串来替换第一层，这两个是从
密钥空间里随机选取的
truly random strings, these two are truly
random picked in the key space, then no
那么没有有效的攻击可以区分这两个分布
efficient adversary should be able to
distinguish these two distributions. In
事实上，如果大家可以区分这两个分布
fact, if you could distinguish these two
distributions, it's easy to show that you
容易证明大家可以破解最初的PRG。好
大家看得出我们进行替换的原因
would break the original PRG. Okay, but
essentially you see that the reason we can
我们之所以可以用真随机值来替换G的输出
do this replacement, we can replace the
output of G, with truly random values, is
是因为PRG的定义所致，PRG的输出
exactly because of the definition of the
PRG, which says the output of the PRG is
和随机不可区分。所以我们也可以把随机数放在那
indistinguishable from random, so we might
as well just put random there, and no
没有有效的攻击可以区分这两个分布
efficient adversary can distinguish the
resulting two distributions. Okay, so far
目前都还不错，现在我们要对左边做同样的事情
so good, but now we can do the same thing
again to the left hand side. In other
换句话说，我们可以用真随机替换这两个伪随机输出
words, we can replace these two pseudo
random outputs, by truly random outputs.
还是因为发生器G是安全的，没有有效的攻击
And again because the generator G is
secure, no efficient adversary can tell
可以区分这两个分布。但不同的是
the difference between these two
distributions. But differently, if an
如果一个攻击者可以区分这两个分布
adversary can distinguish these two
distributions, then we would also give an
我们也可以给出一个对发生器G的攻击
最后，我们最后再做一次
attack on the generator G. And now finally
we're gonna do this one last time. We're
我们用真随机对替换掉这一伪随机对
gonna replace this pseudo random pair by a
truly random pair, and lo and behold we
现在我们获得了我们想要的分布
get the actual distribution that we were
shooting for, we would get a distribution
我们获得了一个由4个独立分组构成的分布
that is really made of four independent
blocks. And so now we have proved this
我们已经证明了这个转换，这两是不可区分的
transition basically that these two
indistinguishable, these two
这两是不可区分的，这两是不可区分的
indistinguishable, and these two
indistinguishable, and therefore these two
因此这两是不可区分的，记为我们想证明的
are indistinguishable, which is what we
wanted to prove. Okay so this is kind of
这是证明的大致想法，严格证明之并不难
the high level idea for the proof, it is
not too difficult to make this rigorous,
不过我只想告诉大家证明的直观想法
but I just wanted to show you kinda
intuition for how the proof works. Well,
如果我们可以扩张发生器的输出
if we were able to extend the generators
outputs once, there's nothing preventing
我们当然可以再做一次，于是就有一发生器G1
us from doing it again so here is a
generator G1 that outputs four elements in
输出密钥空间里的四个元素。记住这里的输出
the key space. And remember the output
here is indistinguishable from our random
与随机四元组不可区分，即为所证
我们完全可以再次应用这个发生器
four tuple, that's what we just proved.
And so there's nothing preventing us from
所以我们会拿着这个发生器，应用于
applying the generator again. So we'll
take the generator apply it to this random
这个看起来像是随机的东西。我们应该可以获得
这个看起来像是随机的东西
looking thing and we should be able to get
this random looking thing. This pair over
这对看起来像是随机的。我们可以做同样的事情
here that's random looking. And we can do
the same thing again, and again, and
一次又一次。现在我们也已经构建了一个新的发生器
可以输出K^8里的元素
again. And now basically we've built a new
generator that outputs elements in K to
而不是K^4里的元素，其证明
the eighth, as opposed to K to the fourth.
And again the proof of security is very
也与我刚刚给大家的非常一致
much the same as the one I just showed you
essentially you gradually change the
把输出变成真随机。所以我们把这转变成真随机
outputs into truly random outputs. So we
would change this to a truly random
然后这里，然后那里，然后这里，然后那里，等等
output, then this, then that, then this,
then that and so on and so forth. Until
最终我们获得了真随机的字符串
finally we get something that's truly
random and therefore the original two
所以我们开始用G2K的两个分布
与真随机不可区分。好的
distributions we started with G2K and
truly random are indistinguishable. Okay,
目前还不错。现在我们有一个发生器，输出K^8中元素
so far so good. So now we have a generator
that outputs elements in K to the eighth.
如果我们获得了3位PRF，换句话说
Now if we do that basically we get a three
bit PRF. In other words, at zero, zero,
在000处，这个PRF会输出这个分组，等等
zero this PRF would output this block, and
so on and so forth until one, one, one it
直到111它会输出这个分组。现在，有趣的是
would output this block. Now the
interesting thing is that in fact this PRF
事实上这个PRF是容易计算的。例如
假设我们想计算PRF在101处的值
is easy to compute. For example, suppose
we wanted to compute the PRF at the point
好，这是个3位PRF。好，101
one zero one. Okay, it's a three bit PRF.
Okay so one zero one. How would we do
我们该怎么办？我们从这个初始密钥K开始
that? Well basically we would start from
the original key K. And now we would apply
现在我们应用发生器G，但我们只关心G输出的右边
the generator G but we would only pay
attention to the right output of G,
因为第一位是1。然后我们再次应用发生器
because the first bit is one. And then we
will apply the generator again, but we
但我们只关注发生器输出的左边
would only pay attention to the left of
the output of the generator because the
因为第二位是0。然后我们再次应用这个发生器
second bit is zero. And then we would
apply the generator again and only pay
只关注右边，因为第三位是1
attention to the right outputs because the
third bit is one and that would be the
那也是最终输出。好，大家可以看到
这就是101的情况
final output. Right, so you can see that,
that lead us to 101, and in fact because
事实上因为整个发生器是伪随机的
the entire generator is pseudo
random, we know that, in particular that,
我们知道这里的输出也是伪随机的。好
这就给了我们一个3位PRF
this output here is pseudo random. Okay,
so this gives us a three bit PRF. Well, if
如果它工作3次，它也完全可以工作N次
it worked three times, there's no reason
why it can't work N times. And so if we
如果我们反复应用这个转换
我们就可以到达GGMPRF
apply this transformation again and again,
we arrive at what's called a GGMPRF. GGM
GGM是指Goldreich, Goldwasser和Micali
stands for Goldreich, Goldwasser and
Micali these are the inventors of
他们是这个PRF的发明者。这个PRF如下工作
this PRF and the way it works is as
follows. So we start off with a generator
我们从一个输出长度是输入长度两倍的PRG出发
我们来构建一个PRF，其定义域很大
just doubles its outputs, and now we're
able to build a PRF that acts on a large
为｛0,1｝^N。N可以是128甚至更大
domain mainly a domain of size zero one to
the N, where N could be as big as 128 or even
我们看，假设我们有｛0,1｝^N里的输入
more. So let's see, suppose we're given an
input in 01 to the N, let me show you how
我来展示如何计算这个PRF。现在大家有个好想法
to evaluate the PRF. Well by now you
should actually have a good idea for how
从最初的密钥开始
to do it. Essentially we start from the
original key and then we apply the
应用发生器根据X0位来选择左边或右边
generator and we take either the left or
the right side depending on the bit X0 and
然后我们得到了下一密钥K1
我们再次应用发生器
then we arrive at the next key, K1. And
then we apply the generator again and we
根据X1位来选择左边或右边，得到下一个密钥
take the left or the right side depending
on X1 and we arrive at the next key. And
然后我们反复这样操作，直到得到输出
then we do this again and again, until
finally we are arrive at the output. So we
我们已经处理了所有位，得到了函数的输出
have processed all end bits, and we arrive
at the output of this function. And
用之前同样的方法，我们可以证明其安全性
basically we can prove security again
pretty much along the same lines as we did
我们可以证明如果G是个安全的PRG
before, and we can show that if G is a
secure PRG, then in fact we get a secure
事实上我们可以获得一个安全的PRF
定义在｛0,1｝^N上的，一个非常大的定义域
PRF, on 01 to the N, on a very large
domain. So that's fantastic. Now we have
很神奇。现在我们有一个可证实安全的PRF
we have essential, we have a PRF that's
provably secure, assuming that the
以安全的发生器为前提。这个发生器
underlying generator is secure, and the
generator is supposedly much easier to
比一个实际的PRF更容易构造。事实上
他可以工作的分组可以是很大
build than an actual PRF. And in fact it
works on blocks that can be very large, in
特别地，｛0,1｝^128，这是我们想要的
particular, 01 to the 128th, which is what
we needed. So you might ask well why isn't
大家可能会问，为什么这个在实际中没有被用到？
原因是，它的速度很慢
this thing being used in practice? And the
reason is, that it's actually fairly slow.
设想一下，我们使用Salsa发生器
So imagine we plug in as a generator we
plug in the Salsa generator. So now to
现在来计算这个PRF在某个128位输入的值
我们必须运行Salsa发生器128次
evaluate this PRF at a 128 bit inputs, we
would basically have to run the Salsa
一次只对应一位输入。然后我们获得了
generator 128 times. One time per bit of
the input. But then we would get a PRF
一个PRF，其运行时间却是原版Salsa的128倍
that's 128 times slower than the original
Salsa. And that's much, much, much slower
这比AES慢太多太多。AES是一个启发性（未经证实）的PRF
但它我们这的要快很多
than AES. AES is a heuristic PRF. But
nevertheless it's much faster then what we
尽管这个构造很优雅
just got here. And so even though this is
a very elegant construction, it's not used
实际构造伪随机函数时却不实用
in practice to build pseudo random
functions although in a week we will be
虽然本周我们还要使用这个构造
来构建一个信息完整性的机制
using this type of construction to build a
message integrity mechanism. So the last
最后一步，现在我们构建了一个PRF
step, is basically now that we've built a
PRF, the questions is whether we can
问题是我们能否构建分组密码。换句话说
actually build the block cypher. In other
words, can we actually build a secure PRP
我们能否从一个安全的PRG构建一个安全的PRP呢？
我们目前所做的都是不可逆的情况
from a secure PRG. Everything we've done
so far is not reversible. Again if you
如果大家看这里的构造，给定最后输出
我们是不能解密的
look at this construction here, we can't
decrypt basically given the final outputs.
不可能回去，至少我们不知道怎么回去
It is not possible to go back or at least
we don't know how to go back the, the
回到最初的输入。所以现在问题是
original inputs. So now the question of
interest is so can we actually solve the
我们能不能解决最初的问题？我们能否
根据安全PRG构建一个分组密码？
problem we wanted solve initially? Mainly,
can we actually build a block cipher from
那么大家想一想，记下答案
a secure PRG? So I'll let you think about
this for a second, and mark the answer. So
当然我希望大家的答案是肯定的
of course I hope everyone said the answer
is yes and you already have all the
大家已经万事俱备了。特别地
大家已经知道了如何从一个伪随机数发生器
ingredients to do it. In particular, you
already know how to build a PRF from a
构建一个PRF。我们说了一旦有了PRF
pseudo random generator. And we said that
once we have a PRF we can plug it into the
我们可以使用Luby-Rackoff构造法
记得是一个三回合的Feistel网络
Luby-Rackoff construction, which if you
remember, is just a three-round Feistel.
我们说了如果大家有了安全的PRF
就可以利用三回合Feistel
So we said that if you plug a secure PRF
into a three-round Feistel, you get a
就可以得到一个安全的PRP。所以
将两者结合起来，我们就能从一个伪随机数发生器
secure PRP. So combining these two
together, basically gives us a secure PRP
得到一个安全的PRP，它可被证明是安全的
from a pseudo random generator. And this
is provably secure as long as the
只要支持它的发生器是安全的。那么这个
结果很美，但很不幸
underlying generator is secure. So it's a
beautiful result but unfortunately again
它也不实用，因为它比类似于AES的
启发性构造要慢很多
it's not used in practice because it's
considerably slower than heuristics
好，本章完结
constructions like AES. Okay so
this completes our module on constructing
我们构造了伪随机置换和函数
pseudo random permutations, and pseudo
random functions. And then in the next
下一章中我们讨论在正常加密中如何使用它们
module we're gonna talk about how to use
these things to do proper encryption.